{
  "reference_number": "11679",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "There is no further time for delay. The seriousness of this issue has been appreciated for decades, with relatively little progress\n made; it is time for bold steps not weasel words and worthy statements of intent. I note that although the issue has been regarded\n as pressing for decades it is difficult to point to any significant way in which our lifestyle, as a high income country, has changed as a\n\n result. This might once have been dismissed as complacency; now it looks like reckless arrogance."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "NZ has to confront the challenge of methane emissions from agriculture, instead of continuing to ring fence and privilege that one\n sector. It is time for the agricultural sector to take responsibility for the environmental damage that it is causing and for NZ to further\n\n diversify its economic activity and progressively direct it away from animal agriculture."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "At the root of this challenge is the unsustainability of life in high income countries. Over coming decades we need to plan a radical\n change in cultural and societal attitudes. This will not be achieved with the urgency required if we continue to buy time by the\n purchasing international carbon units. In fact if anything this is further evidence of high income countries being reluctant to take full\n\n responsibility for their part in causing climate change over the past 100 years. On the subject of taking responsibility, it is time to stop\n prefacing every statement on climate change in relation to NZ with the comment that our we are a low emitter. The proper measure\n here should be the per capita emissions, and by that measure we are one of the worst offenders on the planet. Most New\n\n Zealanders are not even aware of that, and it is well beyond time that they understood the full implications of our way of life and\n economic activity."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "We have already spent far too much time looking for and making excuses for our lack of action. Climate change is the most pressing\n\n challenge facing humanity, and it's time that we treated it as such."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Several of these matters are liable to be exploited to delay the making of necessary difficult decisions. Further delay is simply not an\n\noption."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Although there should be a strong bedrock of climate science expertise; any other areas of expertise should be secondary to that."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Adaptation involves quite a different focus and should be overseen by a separate body, which would of course be informed in its work\n\nby the Climate Change Commission. My concern is that responsibility for adaptation will distract from the substantial urgent mitigation\nstrategies that the Commission will need to focus on."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "It's not clear what the question is referring to, and reference to p47 sheds no additional light."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    }
  ]
}
